Guide to the John Howard Griffin Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series XV. The Jacques Maritain Files
  - Subseries XV.2: Literary Matters
    - Encyclopaedia Britannica To John Howard Griffin, Chicago, IL, 1971, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon) (Box 17, Folder 593)
      [Thanking him for permission to print one of his portraits of Maritain in their Great Ideas Today series
    - World Publishing Company To John Howard Griffin, Cleveland, OH, 1967, (4 t.l.s. (with carbon) (Box 17, Folder 594)
      [With Griffin reply, concerning Maritain portraits for cover of the philosopher's Challenges and Renewals; and also their interest in publishing a book of Merton portraits by Griffin; the Maritain book was published but the Merton book (by World) was not
    - Lawler, Justus George To John Howard Griffin, New York, 1967, (2 t.l.s. (with photocopy article) (Box 17, Folder 595)
      [Editor of Jubilee magazine, at that time (1967) having been-taken over by Herder--and Herder Publishing; many of Griffin's portraits of Maritain, including one for the issue's cover, were published in Jubilee's homage to the philosopher, January 1968; the letters from Lawler are original typescripts; also photocopy of Jubilee
    - John M. Dunaway To the Estate of John Howard Griffin, CT & GA, 1991 & 1992, (4 t.l.s.) (Box 17, Folder 596)
      [Requesting the use of one portrait to be published in Dunaway's Exiles and Fugitives by LSU Press; also a second letter requesting that the same photograph of Maritain be printed in the LSU Press catalogue (1992)
  - Subseries XV.3: The Gwen John Project
    Gwen John, sister of Augustus John, was little known during her lifetime. After her death, her meticulous paintings--especially portraits--became highly regarded. As a friend of the Maritains, she left with them several paintings as gifts (watercolors and gouaches), as well as drawings.
    - Griffin, John Howard Proposal to photograph the Gwen John pieces as an art book, with or without text, and to have the proceeds go to the Maritain Circle housed at the Chateau de Kolbsheim, France, Fort Worth, TX, 13 Aug. 1967, (1 page t.l. (carbon) (Box 17, Folder 597)
    - Grunelius, Alexander Letter of agreement, Cercle d'Etudes Jacques et Raissa Maritain, France, 11 Oct. 1967, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 17, Folder 597)
      [Owner of Kolbsheim, the Grunelius Estate which provided space to artists at no cost, allowing a quiet and elegant setting for artistic retreats. The Maritains and Griffin made many trips there.
    - Mary Taubman To John Howard Griffin, Strosbourg, France, 24 Aug. 1967, (1 a.l.s. 4 page, t.ms. (essay) ) (Box 17, Folder 598)
      [Art critic who was the curator for the Gwen John exhibition at the Tate Gallery, London
    - Antoinette Grunelius To John Howard Griffin, Kolbsheim, France, 1967-1969, (10 a.l.s., 1 a.p.c.s., 1 telegram ) (Box 17, Folder 599)
  - Subseries XV.4: The Peasant of Garonne
    For an in-depth discussion of the controversial ideas in Jacques Maritain's last book, a reading of the Griffin interview with Maritain is illuminating. However, there is a story behind the book's publication in America, and this story behind the story is revealed in the correspondences that follow. This short morality play features a French publisher, several American publishers, a French literary agent based in Manhattan, a translator, concerned friends like Thomas Merton and John Howard Griffin, and the elderly layman who called himself "the peasant of Garonne" (Jacques Maritain). Georges Borchardt, a literary agent for the Paris publishing house, Declee de Brouwer (which published the original edition of Peasant) offered both the Maritain book and French edition of Raissa Maritain's Journal to Charles Scribner's Sons of New York. The legendary Scribner, a long-time friend of the Maritains and the publisher of many of the philosopher's books in English, was interested in Peasant but not the poetic reflections of Raissa's Journal. Displeased with Scribner and Borchardt, Maritain wrote the publisher to say that either both books would be published by his old publisher or neither would be published under his imprint. And he turned the proceedings over to his friend, John Howard Griffin, who agreed to find an appropriate American publisher for both books, as well as translators.. However, as Griffin made contacts with publishers--and had interest from Arabel Porter at New American Library and Ralph Manheim at Harcourt--Borchardt was contacting other New York publishers with the encouragement of the original French publisher, Deciee de Brouwer. Borchardt managed to interest Joseph Cunneen, the religious editor at Holt, Rinehart and Winston, in Peasant, reaching preliminary agreement on a contract. When Maritain hear of this from Cunneen, he wrote to say that he was not against Holt publishing his book, but insisted that Griffin and not Borchardt handle the negotiations (as well as choose the translator). At the same time, Borchardt wrote Griffin to say that he had came to terms with Holt on behalf of Declee de Brouwer. Griffin, in an agony of embarrassment because this was exactly the sort of tension he wanted to avoid for Maritain, was forced to alert NAL and Harcourt of the mess, as well as correspond with Holt to make certain that the contract did not violate Maritain's wishes.. Finally, after several rounds of letters, the issue was clarified.. Holt would publish Peasant, Borchardt would be the link between Holt and Declee de Brouwer, and Griffin would select the translator. In the shuffle, there was no mention of Raissals Journal, so Griffin went elsewhere with that project, eventually landing it with Magi Books several years later. Michael Cuddihy was chosen to translate with the understanding that his English version would be examined by Griffin, Thomas Merton, and Joseph Evans of the Maritain society -- all trusted Maritain friends and translators (from French) in their own right.. All the preceding took place from November 1966 until the spring of 1967. At that point, a complete retyping of the Cuddihy translation had to be made at Holt, and Maritain became concerned about the slow progress. For some of the others there was a greater problem: No one was very impressed with the translation. So, after making changes suggested by Merton and Evans, Griffin took the translation to France, spending several weeks working it over with Maritain, who was not impressed with Cuddihy's work either. The accepted translation was dispatch by Maritain to Griffin's hands and then on to Joseph Cunneen at Holt, who made the point that not only had Cuddihy improved his work as he went along (and that his work had been further improved by Merton and Griffin especially), but that he was not pleased with Maritain's low opinion of the translation or with the philosopher's changes which he felt were neither "that extensive nor that helpful". When all the smoke of ego had cleared, the book was published by Holt with a portrait of Maritain (by Griffin) on its dust jacket. It sold well and went into a paperback-reprint by MacMillan (again with Griffin's portrait as the cover). Extensive detail is revealed by the actual documents
    - Maritain, Jacques To Charles Scribner, [Haute-Garonne, France?], 21 Dec. 1966, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 17, Folder 600)
    - Maritain, Jacques To Joseph Cunneen of Holt, Rinehart and Winston, [Haute-Garonne, France], 23 Nov. 1966, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 17, Folder 601)
      [In English
    - Cunneen, Jopseph To Jacques Maritain & John Howard Griffin, New York, 17 Nov. 1966, (1 page t.l.s. (with related material) (Box 17, Folder 601)
    - Griffin, John Howard To Arabel Porter of New American Library, Fort Worth, TX, 17 Dec. 1966, (2 page t.l. (carbon) (Box 17, Folder 602)
    - Manheim, Ralph To John Howard Griffin, [New York], 21 Nov. 1966, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 17, Folder 603)
    - Cuddihy, Michael To John Howard Griffin, Tucson, AZ, 26 Dec. 1966, (2 page t.l.s. (with related material) (Box 17, Folder 604)
    - Borchardt, George To John Howard Griffin, New York, 14 & 19 Dec. 1966, (2 t.l.s. (with carbons) (Box 17, Folder 605)
      [Also two original typescript letters from Borchardt to Griffin; both men sadly lamenting the confusion and pleading innocence (although it was Borchardt who, in fact, caused all the confusion)
    - Desclee de Brouwer To John Howard Griffin, Paris, 1966 - 1970, (5 t.l.s. (with carbon and notes) (Box 17, Folder 606)
    - Young, William To John Howard Griffin, Toronto, 21 Jan. & 15 Feb. 1969, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon) (Box 17, Folder 607)
    - Suther, Marshall To John Howard Griffin, Paris, 27 July 1971, (1 page a.l.s. (with carbon) (Box 17, Folder 608)
      [With JHG carbon reply
    - Suther, Judith To John Howard Griffin, NC, 7 June 1980, (3 page t.l.s.) (Box 17, Folder 609)
    - John Coleman To John Howard Griffin, Paris, 29 March 1967, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 17, Folder 610)
    - Bernard Berhand To John Howard Griffin, Paris, 21 March 1967, (2 page a.l.s.) (Box 17, Folder 611)
    - Parbot, Michel To John Howard Griffin, Paris, 15 Feb. 1967, (1 page t.l.s.) (Box 17, Folder 612)
    - Editions Gallimard & Edition des Derni res To John Howard Griffin, Paris, 3 Feb. 1967 & 8 June 1973, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 17, Folder 613)
  - Subseries XV.5: Jacques Maritain: Homage in Words and Pictures
    A 64-page large format book of photographs and texts, published by Magi Books in 1974. This is the same Albany, NY publisher who brought out Raissa's Journal and also Maritain's Notebooks. All three of these books are still in print. The Homaqe consists of an essay on Maritain by philosopher Yves Simon; this one of many written by a close friend and colleague, who illuminates Maritain's ideas and personality for the general reader. The second part of this "homage in words" is by John Howard Griffin, excerpts from journals kept while visiting with Martain in Princeton (1962), Fort Worth and Gethsemani (1966), Kolbsheim (1967) and Toulouse (1970).. The book ends with Griffin's 1973 entry about the last days of the philosopher. The book opens with a Foreword by Anthony Simon, son of Yves Simon, that reflects on the friendship of his father and Maritain. The magnificent photos throughout the book are by Griffin
    - Griffin, John Howard Journal entries re. Jacques Maritain, [Fort Worth, TX], [1970s], (38 page t.ms. (carbon, with Griffin's ms. corrections) (Box 17, Folder 614)
      [Composed from several entries in his journals; comparing these dated entries with the original versions (of the same dates) suggests some polishing but not massive revision
    - Anthony Simon "Foreword" to Homage, South Bend, IN, [Early 1970 & 1971], (4 page t.ms. (photocopy), 10 page t.ms. (photocopy), 9 page t.ms. (photocopy), 1 t.l.) (Box 17, Folder 615)
    - Gallagher, Thomas To John Howard Griffin, Albany, NY, 1970 - 1978, (6 t.l.s, 1 t.l.) (Box 17, Folder 616)
      [Publisher; these discuss developing ideas about the book's text, format, photographs, followed by plans for promotion
    - Simon, Anthony To John Howard Griffin, South Bend, IN, 1968-1980, (3 a.l.s., 16 t.l.s.) (Box 17, Folder 617)
      [Also a photocopy of Maritain letter to Simon; and Maritain Symposium materials from the American Maritain Assoc. of which Simon is secretary
    - Griffin, John Howard To Tony Simon, Fort Worth, TX, 1970-1976, (4 t.l. (carbon) (Box 17, Folder 618)
      [In one of these Griffin discusses his time in the French Underground and how Yves Simon understood the degree of French collaboration with the Nazis which was not realized by those at ground zero (see Simon's book about the Vichy conspiracy). (Plus review-essays and short newspaper reviews)
    - Simon, Anthony "Foreword" & Yves R. Simon essay, [n.p.], [n.d.], (7 page proof & notes) (Box 17, Folder 619)
    - Jacques Maritain: Homage In Words and Pictures, [n.p.], [n.d.], (40 sheets page proof) (Box 17, Folder 620)
    - Simon, Paule Jacques Maritain: Homage In Words and Pictures, [n.p.], [n.d.], (159 page t.ms. (photocopy; French translation) (Box 17, Folder 621)
- Series XVI. A Time To Be Human
  Commissioned by MacMillan as a book on racism for young adults, A Time To Be Human was published in 1977. It was Griffin's last book about racism (and human rights issues), as well as a summation of all his work in this area:. With Black Like Me and The Church and the Black Man it forms a remarkable trilogy. The text reprises the Black Like Me experience with different anecdotes and a re-evaluation of the 1960s; and it draws on many of his Sepia articles from the 1970s, as well as updated materials. Begun as a tape recording, Griffin worked up the published book through three manuscript drafts, giving the scholar a rare overview of his method.. The series includes Griffin's Original Typescript of the First Draft, a 73 page manuscript, with the author's corrections. Major changes can be studied in Griffin's Second Draft, also the Original Typescript, which runs to 71 manuscript pages. Finally, there is the 75 page manuscript of the Final Draft (a photocopy), including both the author's and the editor's changes. The Editor in this instance was David Reuther of MacMillan, who had made Griffin's acquaintance through correspondence regarding another MacMillan publication for young adults--the Cornelia and Irving Sussman biography of Thomas Merton. Griffin provided the cover photographs for the Merton biography, as well as advice to its authors, the husband and wife team who were his close friends (see their correspondence in Series VII)
  - MacMillan Publishing Co. Inc. To John Howard Griffin, New York, 1975-1977, (11 t.l. (signed David Reuther & Michelle Gale) (Box 18, Folder 622)
    [With Griffin's carbon replies
  - Griffin, John Howard Outline of the Introduction, [Fort Worth, TX], [ca. 1975], (1 page t.ms.) (Box 18, Folder 623)
  - Griffin, John Howard List of photographs (most by JHG) to illustrate the book, [Fort Worth, TX], [ca. 1975], (1 page t.ms.) (Box 18, Folder 623)
  - Griffin, John Howard Notes and drafts, [Forth Worth, TX], [ca. 1975], (7 page t.ms. (carbon, with Griffin's ms. corrections) (Box 18, Folder 623)
  - First draft, [Forth Worth, TX], [ca. 1975], (73 page t.ms. (with Griffin's ms. corrections) (Box 18, Folder 624)
  - Second draft, [Forth Worth, TX], [ca. 1975], (82 page t.ms. (with Griffin's ms. corrections) (Box 18, Folder 625)
  - Second draft, [Forth Worth, TX], [ca. 1975], (80 page t.ms. (photocopy, with Griffin's ms. corrections) (Box 18, Folder 626)
  - Galleys, [Forth Worth, TX], [ca. 1975], (30 galley sheets (with Griffin's ms. corrections) (Box 18, Folder 627-629)
- Series XVII.The Decade of the Seventies
  During his last decade, Griffin concentrated most of his energies on the research and writing of the official Biography of Thomas Merton--a project he relinquished to a second biographer (Michael Mott) in 1977. In order to support his family, he also became an editor for Sepia, the monthly magazine which had serialized his "Journey into Shame" articles which eventually became Black Like Me. Also, he lectured at universities on the theme of racism, but he spoke about Thomas Merton's spirituality as well. He traveled increasingly to Toronto, where he developed a huge Catholic student following, lecturing in Canada more often than in the States. By 1976, he experienced a serious decline in health, with complications that eventually ended his hope of completing the Merton biography. But from 1969-1972, he was. in reasonably good health, and completed most of the Merton research in a series of retreats at the monk's hermitage on the grounds of the Abbey of Gethsemani in Kentucky. Series XIII and XIV cover that period and document the Merton connection. Series XVIII is the journal he kept at Gethsemani, a book he worked on in 1979 and 1980, the year he died.. Even though he worked most diligently on the Merton materials until 1977, he did manage to write and publish a wide variety of shorter pieces and complete an immense number of photographic works.
  - Subseries XVII.1: General
    - Twelve Photographic Portraits. A Chapbook published by Unicorn Press featuring portraits of Roland Hayes, Zara. Nelsova, Mark Van Doren, Lili Kraus, John Jacob Niles, Annie Fischer, Wendell Berry, Denise Levertov, Maxwell Gesmar, Thomas Merton and Brother Lavrans Nielsen, painter and monk at Gethsemani, Greensboro, NC: The Unicorn Press, 1973, (1 volume (paperback) (Box 18, Folder 630)
    - Unicorn Press To John Howard Griffin, Santa Barbara, CA, 1969 & 1970, (1 t.l.s, 4 a.l. (signed Teo Savory) (Box 18, Folder 631)
      [With Griffin's carbon and photocopy of article on Merton's friendship
    - Pilgrimage, [Fort Worth, TX], [1970s], (7 pp. t.ms. (carbon, with Griffin's ms. corrections) (Box 18, Folder 632)
      [Became a Latitudes Press chapbook in 1985. This was the only piece of fiction Griffin wrote after the 1950s, except for time spent on revising earlier unpublished novels (during the 196Os). With related correspondence from Renaissance Publications Co, Inc., 1973.
    - Griffin, John Howard Review of George Woodcock's biography Thomas Merton, Monk and Poet, (3 page t.ms (carbon, with corrections) (Box 18, Folder 633)
    - Griffin, John Howard Review of Thomas Merton's Asian Journal, [Fort Worth, TX], [1973], (9 page t.ms.(carbon, with corrections) (Box 18, Folder 634)
    - Griffin, John Howard Outline for nine sessions of a seminar on Merton he gave in Toronto, [Toronto], [1970s], (1 page t.ms.(carbon) (Box 18, Folder 635)
    - Griffin, John Howard "The Terrain of Physical Pain", Pilgrim Press, 1970, (14 page photocopy of essay) (Box 18, Folder 636)
      [One of Griffin's very finest essays, written from an objective point of view that masks his deeply personal involvement with physical pain, its levels of consciousness and possible adaptations to spiritual awakening; from the pages of Creative Suffering an- Anthology by Pilgrim Press, 1970
    - Griffin, John Howard "My Book", Fort Worth, TX, 1973, (5 pp. t.ms.(carbon, with corrections) (Box 18, Folder 637)
      [A personal essay that discusses the handful of books which "have the capacity to transform one's life"--that is, books in Griffin's experience as a reader. Several books are discussed, but his focus is on the autobiography of the photographer Alvin Langdon Coburn. It was written for Way magazine and published in a series
    - Griffin, John Howard To The Editor of "Way" magazine, Fort Worth, TX, 1973, (t.l.(carbon) ) (Box 18, Folder 637)
    - Griffin, John Howard "From Boy to Writer in One Night", Cincinnati, OH: Writer's Digest, 1970, (5 page Photocopy of article) (Box 18, Folder 638)
      [Autobiographical anecdote about spending the night in Paris under a stairwell as a teenager which spins into some tips about turning experience into writing; one of only two Griffin pieces on the art of writing. From the anthology Handbook of Short Story Writing, published by The Writer's Digest in 1973
    - Griffin, John Howard "Racism 1974-1975", Huy, Belgium, October 1974, (16 page pamphlet) (Box 18, Folder 639)
      [An editorial on page 2, 3, 16 of the Belgian periodical "From Heart to Heart" published by the Dominique Pire Foundation
    - Griffin, John Howard Review of Expectations 1975, an anthology of children's literature in Braille for blind. children, published by the Braille Institute of America, Fort Worth, TX, [1975], (3 page t.ms.(carbon) (Box 18, Folder 640)
      [Published in The New York Times Book Review in 1975; Griffin was blind for a decade
    - Griffin, John Howard "J. Edgar Hoover's Interference With Church Leaders", [Fort Worth, TX], 1976, (3 page t.ms.(carbon, with corrections) (Box 18, Folder 681)
      [An article about FBI interference with Dr. Martin Luther King and other black leaders; with a copy of The Continuing Inquiry in which it was published.
  - Subseries XVII.2: The Sepia Magazine File
    Sepia, originally based in Fort Worth, moved to Chicago in the 1970s
    - Ben Burns To John Howard Griffin, Chicago, IL, 1974, (4 t.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 642)
    - Griffin, John Howard "Revolution in Medical Care", Fort Worth, TX, [1970s], (9 page t.ms.(carbon) and outlines) (Box 18, Folder 643)
      [Article about clinics for the poor, run by the poor; published with Griffin photographs
    - Griffin, John Howard "Moore's Seafood", [Fort Worth, TX], [1970s], (7 page t.ms.(carbon, and outlines) (Box 18, Folder 644)
      [Article about Joe Moore, black Alabama businessman; published with JHG photos
    - Griffin, John Howard "Paul Cuffe", Fort Worth, TX, [1970s], (16 page t.ms.(carbon) (Box 18, Folder 645)
      [Excellent piece of Black History about little-known sea captain and philanthropist
    - "A Decade Later: The Unsolved Mystery of The Malcolm X Murder", Fort Worth, TX, [1970s], (19 page t.ms.(carbon) (Box 18, Folder 646)
    - "How Wallace Has Changed on Race Relations", [Fort Worth, TX], [1970s], (10 page t.ms.(carbon, with related t.l.s. & invitation) (Box 18, Folder 687)
      [Article on Governor Wallace that suggests that the Alabama icon's image had been changed by a new press kit, in 1974, but black citizens of Alabama were skeptical.
    - "Gospel Singer Kenneth Glover", Fort Worth, TX, 1973, (9 page t.ms.(carbon) (Box 18, Folder 688)
      [With an autograph letter from Glover to Griffin
    - "Release of Mississippi Klansman Stirs Old Fears", Fort Worth, TX, 1973, (9 page t.ms.(carbon) (Box 18, Folder 649)
      [Article about the Klan's murder of Vernon Dahmer a leader in the Hattiesburg black community
    - Griffin, John Howard To Ben Burns, Forth Worth, TX, 22 Feb. 1973, (1 t.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 649)
      [Concerning later developments in the story
  - Subseries XVII.3: Media
    - Articles on Griffin in Newsweek, etc., 1970 and 1977 (Box 18, Folder 650)
    - Krebs, A.Y. Article/Interview of Griffin in U.S. Catholic, [Fort Worth, TX], 1968, (13 page t.ms.(carbon) (Box 18, Folder 651)
    - Krebs, A.Y. To John Howard Griffin, San Francisco & Washington, DC, 15 Sept. 1967 - 1 Sept. 1980, (3 letters ) (Box 18, Folder 651)
    - Griffin, John Howard Interview from Fort Worth magazine, Fort Worth, TX, 1974, (7 page photocopy) (Box 18, Folder 652)
    - Smith, Thurston "Dying Like Me": Interview with Griffin, U.S. Catholic, November 1977, (7 page photocopy) (Box 18, Folder 653)
      [Griffin's last interview published in U.S. Catholic; contains insights on pain, dying, and spirituality; one of his best interviews
  - Subseries XVII.4: Correspondence
    - King, Coretta Scott To John Howard Griffin, Atlanta, GA, 7 September 1977, (1 telegram) (Box 18, Folder 654)
    - Kozol, Jonathan To John Howard Griffin, Boston, MA, 1972-1978, (3 a.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 655)
    - Geismar, Maxwell To John Howard Griffin, Harrison, NY, 1970-1978, (9 t.l.s., 1 telegram) (Box 18, Folder 656)
    - Doherty, Catherine To John Howard Griffin, Ontario, 1970-1978, (17 t.l.s., 1 a.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 657)
      [Old Merton friend and founder of Madonna House in Ontario, Canada; plus one carbon typescript response from Griffin
    - Brannin, Carl To John Howard Griffin, Dallas, TX, 7 April 1978, (1 page a.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 658)
      [Texas writer and regular contributor to The Texas Observer, concerning the Observer's sending of 500 copies of Black Like Me to Texas colleges
    - Upper Midwest Writers' Conference To John Howard Griffin, Bemidji, MN, 1976, (3 t.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 659)
      [With t.l. (carbon) response from Griffin
    - Courtney, Lucille H. To John Howard Griffin, Shevlin, MN, 1976, (2 t.l.s. (with carbon replies) (Box 18, Folder 660)
      [About her novel
    - John Frederick Nims To John Howard Griffin, Chicago & Lake Forest, IL, 1976, (2 t.l.s.) (Box 18, Folder 661)